Peter S. Barth Papers
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Peter S. Barth Papers.
1971-1972.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Barth, Peter S.
.5 linear feet.
Peter S. Barth, retired professor and former Head of the Economics Department at the University of Connecticut, was appointed Executive Director of the National Commission on State Workmen's Compensation Laws. The collection contains annotated photocopies of the hearings and statements presented to the Commission on for discussion in 1971-1972.
MSS19970015
Biography
Peter S. Barth, retired professor and former Head of the Economics Department at the University of Connecticut, was active in the fields of workmen's compensation, manpower, and labor markets. After receiving his Ph.D. in 1965, Barth was a professor at Ohio State University. A lecturer and advisor for several governmental institutions, Barth was appointed as a Brookings Institute Economic Policy Fellow for 1971-1972 and then Director of the Office of Research with the U.S. Department of Labor (1972-1973). Barth was a professor of Economics at the University of Connecticut from 1973 until his retirement.
The National Commission on State Workmen's Compensation Laws was created in Section 27 of the Occupational Safety and Health Administration legislation passed in 1970. The Commission's purpose was to issue a report based on its findings, the first time a federal level agency examined individual workmen's compensation laws.
President Richard M. Nixon appointed the members of the National Commission on Workmen's Compensation Laws, and asked Barth to serve as executive director. His duties included hiring staff, organization of the hearings, identification of witnesses, and oversight of Commission activities.
During the summer of 1972, two publications resulted from the Commission, Supplemental Studies of National Commission on Workmen's Compensation Laws and Compendium on Workemen's Compensation Laws. The Report of the National Commission on Workmen's Compensation was submitted to the President and Congress as specified in the 1970 legislation.
Following the Commission's work, a number of states re-examined their workmen's compensation laws and made revisions and improvements.
Scope and Content
The Peter S. Barth Papers consists of annotated, photocopied transcripts of nine hearings held by the Commission in several differenct American cities. In addition, two folders contain separate statements submitted to the Commission. The numbers of the hearings are not necessarily in sequential order, but have been arranged chronologically according to the dates of the hearings.
The hearings permitted an opportunity for interested parties to express their views on the adequacy, promptness and equitableness of the present workmen's compensation laws and their suggested recoomendations for improvements. The Commission also accepted written statements in addition to personal testimony. A large number of individuals and groups submitted statements and recommendations including doctors, congressmen, unions and workers' organizations, industry and manufacturers' associations, utilities and private citizens. Contained within the testimony are an assortment of charts, graphs, and summaries of data pertaining to workmen's compensation topics.
Arrangement
Series I: National Commission on State Workmen's Compensation Laws ( 1971-1972 ) contains annotated photocopies of the hearings and statements presented to the Commission for discussion.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut labor. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Final Report of the Blue Ribbon Commission on Fair Wages Dodd
Impact of Provider Choice on Workers' Compensation Costs and Outcomes Dodd
Outcomes for Injured Workers in California, Massachusetts, Pennsylvania and Texas Dodd
Outcomes for Injured Workers in Texas Dodd
Permanent Partial Disability Benefits: Interstate Differences Dodd
Workers' Compensation in Florida: Administrative Inventory Dodd
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Barth, Peter S., 1937-
Subjects:
Worker's compensation--Law and legislation--United States.; Connecticut. Workmen's Compensation Commission.
Document Types:
Photocopies.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. Barth in September 1980.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: National Commission on State Workmen's Compensation Laws, 1971-1972
  - Subseries A: Hearings, 1971-1972
    - Washington, D.C., 1971 September 22 - 23 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Chicago, Illinois, 1971 October 4 - 5 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Boston, Massachusetts, 1971 October 18 - 19 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - San Francisco, California, 1971 November 15 - 17 (Box 1:, Folder 4-5)
    - Dallas, Texas, 1971 November 29 - 30 (Box 1:, Folder 6-7)
    - Washington, D.C., 1971 December 13 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Atlanta, Georgia, 1972 January 10 - 11 (Box 1:, Folder 9-10)
    - Washington, D.C., 1972 January 24 - 26 (Box 1:, Folder 11-12)
    - New York, New York, 1972 March 20 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Subseries B: Separate Statements, 1971-1972
    - A - E, 1971-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - F - Z, 1971-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 15)